<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Queen, at White-Hall, on Sunday, Aug. 16, 1691 by Nathanael Resbury ...</title>
            <author>Resbury, Nathanael, 1643-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12711</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13133621</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13133621</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97879</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57062)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97879)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 749:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Queen, at White-Hall, on Sunday, Aug. 16, 1691 by Nathanael Resbury ...</title>
                  <author>Resbury, Nathanael, 1643-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Bennet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half title: Mr. Resbury's sermon preached before the Queen, at White-Hall, on Sunday, Aug. 16, 1691.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Job XXXVI, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97879:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97879:1"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Resburys</hi> SERMON Preached before the QUEEN, AT WHITE-HALL. On <hi>Sunday, Aug.</hi> 16. 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:97879:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97879:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOB XXXVI. 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Behold God is great, and we know him not, neither can the number of his years be ſearched out.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words are part of a long diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe that <hi>Elihu</hi> took up with <hi>Job,</hi> after his three friends had ended theirs. This perſon, perhaps a <hi>Syrian</hi> born, and of the kindred and family of <hi>Abraham,</hi> tho of younger years than the other three, yet ſeems of deeper judgment, ſtronger reaſoning, leſs affected piety, and one that fram'd the method of his diſcourſe to a better deſign, as he had grounded it upon a better foundation than the other three had done.</p>
            <p>He apprehends <hi>Job</hi> as having a little too much inſiſted upon his own Innocency, and ſo, by juſtifying himſelf too warmly, had ſeem'd to glance obliquely upon God; as if
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97879:3"/>by that ſevere uſage of his Providence, God had dealt in ſomething an unjuſtifiable rigour with him. The part therefore that <hi>Elihu</hi> takes, is, not ſo much to charge <hi>Job</hi> with ſome unknown wickedneſſes which his friends had been loading him with, becauſe of the preſent condition they ſaw him in. But to juſtifie God in his dealings with him, who knew his own holy ends and deſigns in all, tho man is not able reach or to fathom them. My Text is in that part of the argument where <hi>Elihu</hi> is ſetting forth the perfections of God, which to us are ſo incomprehenſible; His power, his greatneſs, his eternity, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo infinitely beyond the reach or compaſs of humane underſtanding, ſhou'd keep the man in ſo humble and reſign'd a ſenſe of God, as not to cheriſh the leaſt irreverent thought of him, let the condition be never ſo miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to which he may be reduc'd.</p>
            <p>In the words we have laid before us, 1. The greatneſs of God, infinitely ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our knowledge of him; <hi>Behold, God is great, and we know him not.</hi> 2. His Eternity, not to be brought within the compaſs of our numbers; <hi>Neither can the number of his years
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97879:3"/>be ſearched out.</hi> By both which is intimated to us, how very ſhort and imperfect all the knowledge we can have of God in this World ought to be eſteem'd; how ſcanty all the conceptions we can frame of his Majeſty or Eternity? Perfections infinitely ſurpaſſing all our meaſures, either as we are mortal, or finite and limited creatures. This I ſhall a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle illuſtrate, and then draw ſome uſeful infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences from the whole.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To illuſtrate the thing; <hi>viz.</hi> How infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely ſhort we are in our higheſt conceptions of God, while we are in this World. We may ask the ſame queſtion ſtill with <hi>Zophar</hi> the <hi>Naamathite,</hi> Job 11.7. <hi>Canſt thou by ſearching find out God? canſt thou find out the Almighty to perfection?</hi> This may appear, if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how imperfect our knowledge is, either as to 1. The Divine nature; or 2. His decrees or counſels; or 3. His works either of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Providence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the Divine nature: It is ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration how incompetent humane nature is herein, when we conſider that any part of it has ſunk ſo low in its ſpeculations concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, ſo far ſhort of his immenſe and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97879:4"/>boundleſs, his pure and inviſible nature, as not only to make Gods of men, and adore them, but to fancy a Divinity even in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and Dogs, and Fiſh; the trunks of old and overgrown Trees, in Leeks and Oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and what not! It is not more evident ſtill, were we to look among the wiſer Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens who made it the buſineſs of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to enquire into the nature of the <hi>chief good,</hi> who after they had rais'd their minds much beyond the common pitch of men of that age, yet after their moſt labour'd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearches, have been fain to confeſs that God was ſomething not only inviſible, but unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible. <hi>Plato</hi> tells us, <hi>it is impoſſible to find out God, and as impoſſible it would be to expreſs him, or communicate the notion of him when once found out.</hi> So <hi>Xenophon, God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the great and the powerful, who is in every ones view, and yet, what his form and eſſence is, is evident to none but himſelf, who makes all things clear and conſpecious by his own light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuch thoughts as theſe, though the higheſt flights among the wiſeſt Philoſophers, need not be much inſiſted upon. For we may obſerve it, in the H. Scriptures, where God
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97879:4"/>has condeſcended to make as plain revelations of himſelf as he thought fit; when <hi>Moſes</hi> made requeſt for a fuller diſcovery of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he tells him how incompetent this ſtate of life is for beholding or knowing him aright. Exod. 33.20. <hi>Thou canſt not ſee my face, for there ſhalls no man ſee me and live:</hi> That is, thou canſt have no proper conceptions of my nature and eſſence, for there is no mortal in this ſtate of life capable of the Speculation. This is ſaid to <hi>Moſes,</hi> who yet was bleſt with ſuch lintimacies, that it is ſaid, <hi>God ſpake to him face to face, as a man ſpeaketh to his friend,</hi> Exod. 23.10. Yet is he in this place aſſur'd, that this diſtant, obnoxious, mortal ſtate of life, is not the ſtate where the Divinity is pleas'd to make any adequate diſplays of his incomprehenſible nature, but reſerves that for the happineſs of the other World. Hence is God pleas'd ſo far to conſider the infancy and childiſhneſs of this ſtate, that he does in the H. Scriptures (if I may ſo expreſs it) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> he attributes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf what is moſt fitted to our ſenſes, and therefore repreſents himſelf by <hi>hands,</hi> and <hi>eyes,</hi> and <hi>ears;</hi> by all the ſhapes of men, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97879:5"/>human paſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are infinitely below his immenſeland ſpiritual nature, to which <hi>no mortal eye</hi> can approach. He gives us notions of his mercy, by that of an indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and compaſſionate father; and of his juſtice, by that of a ſevere and impartial Judge; and of his power, by that of a Crown'd and Scepter'd King; and of his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by that of a liberal and rich Houſholder, and of his Eternity, by that of an old man, or the <hi>Ancient of Days.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which we ought to make ſo awful and reverend an uſe of, as to look upon them only as Condeſcenſions in God to help us in our contemplations of the divine Nature, not to make them the boundaries and limits of our thoughts. And yet, they are a ſtanding ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that the wiſe God, who knows our frame, knows how incapable we are without ſuch condeſcentions to frame any uſeful, or comfortable Ideas of him. And indeed, ſo far are we owing to theſe lower helps of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, that 'tis more than probable, where the minds of men are wholly deſtitute, even of theſe Rudiments they are ſo far from know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing agreeably of the divine Nature,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97879:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>that they have not the leaſt thoughts or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciouſneſs of God at all. I know ſome have made it an Argument againſt the Atheiſt, that there is no Nation under heaven ſo bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, no part of mankind ſo ſalvage, but they have naturally and inſeparably ſome notion and ſenſe of God, and are apt of themſelves, and in the natural tendency of their own thoughts to offer at ſome kind of Worſhip. But I fear, this is <hi>gratis dictum,</hi> ſooner ſaid than prov'd. Hiſtories give us frequent inſtances of ſeveral regions of a wild and uncultivated ſort of Mankind, that give no vilible intimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at all, by which a man might gueſs they have any ſenſe or apprehenſion of God. This is true indeed, that no one endu'd with reaſon, however void of all thoughts of this nature he may have been, but when the notion comes to be offer'd him, and he is told there is a God above that gave him his being, and that governs the world, he ſpeedily embraces it as highly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and finds a natural and ready inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſo great and probable a truth. And this gives the Argument as ſtrong a force againſt the Atheiſt, in that, the ready compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the mind with all ſuch notions when
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97879:6"/>firſt offer'd, ſeems a demonſtration that the thing it ſelf has a native and original truth in it, which needs only to be brought to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and then reaſon falls in immediately with it. But this is certain; as there may be that failure and defect of Reaſon in ſome parts of the World, where barbarous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind may either have loſt all notions of God, or at leaſt have taken up ſome, that are no more ſuited to the divine nature, than the conjectures of a man born blind would be in the deſcription of colours, or the figures and ſhapes of things. So, thoſe that have the greateſt advantages of revelation by the word of God himſelf, and have improv'd theſe advantages by the greateſt induſtry and enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereinto, yea, that have wrought their minds into ſome participation of the divine nature, by labour'd meditation, fall infinitely ſhort of all juſt and adequate conceptions of God. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. We are greatly to ſeek in the firſt notion of God, that he is <hi>a Spirit:</hi> The Scripture tells us, <hi>God is a Spirit,</hi> but we are no more able to conceive what the nature of a Spirit is, than the Child in the Womb apprehends
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97879:6"/>what the nature of his being and ſuſtenance is there. To ſay the truth, were the great ſearcher of hearts, but to lay to our charge all thoſe abſurd Idolatries we commit, in the odd conceptions, the mean and bodily ſhapes we frame of God in our imaginations, whiles we offer at the moſt ſolemn acts of worſhip toward him, we might periſh under the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of our moſt holy things, and the guilt of our moſt labour'd endeavours in devotion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As we are to ſeek in the notion of a Spirit, ſo no leſs are we in that deep and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wondring myſtery of the <hi>Trinity in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> which, upon the ſtrength of Divine revelation we juſtly believe and adore. We are indeed ſure, from the H. Scriptures, that the Father is God, and that Jeſus Chriſt the Son is not only God too, but was ſo from all Eternity, and that the H. Ghoſt is no leſs God, than the Father and the Son. We alſo know, from the ſame expreſs revelation that we are to own and worſhip no other than the <hi>One only,</hi> and true God. Theſe things are certain matter of Divine revelation, and being ſo, we have all imaginable reaſon to believe and embrace them. But then how theſe three diſtinct Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97879:7"/>ſhould be ſo united in one undivided na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that while we worſhip three Perſons, we ſtill do worſhip but one God, this is a myſtery reſerv'd to be unfolded in the other world on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>We may, perhaps, endeavour to illuſtrate the notion by ſome faint and imperfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances, but alas! they are ſo faint and imperfect, that they rather ſerve to darken and obſcure it ſtill more.</p>
            <p n="2">II. As we are very ſhort in apprehending the <hi>Nature</hi> of God, ſo are we no leſs as to his <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Counſels.</hi> The one is the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the other, we therefore muſt needs conjecture uncertainly about his Decrees, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are ſo diſtant, and ſo incompetent in all our Speculations about the Divine Nature. There have been warm and heated diſputes about theſe things amongſt aſſuming men. The Decrees of God have been canvaſt and talkt over by ſome, as if they were the very rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Religion, and might be the firſt learnt and underſtood; when in the mean time, the duſt that diſputes have raiſed in things of ſo high and unſearchable a Nature, have only ſerv'd to hurt the Eyes of both the contending
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97879:7"/>Parties, that they have ſeen the leſs for their warmth in arguing. <hi>What man knoweth the things of a man, ſave the Spirit of a man? Even ſo the things of God, knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.11. It is an excellent paſſage in the Apocryphal book of Wiſdom to this purpoſe. Chap. 4. from v. 13 ad finem. <hi>What man is he that can know the Counſel of God, or who can think what the will of the Lord is? For the thoughts of mortal men are miſerable, and our devices are but uncertain, for the corruptible body preſſeth down the ſoul, and the earthly taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle weigheth down the mind that muſeth upon many things. And hardly do we gueſs aright at things that are upon the Earth, and with labour dowe find the things that are before us; but the things that are in heaven who hath ſearched out? and thy Counſel who hath known? Except thou give Wiſdom and ſend thy Holy Spirit from above!</hi> It is plain how ſhort we are in our thoughts of this kind, not only from the irreconcileable differences about theſe things, but alſo the infinite difficulties wherewith both ways of thinking are perplext. Thus when any would be point blank repreſenting God, as from all eternity chooſing out ſome few for everlaſting
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97879:8"/>happineſs, and decreeing the reſt of mankind abſolutely to eternal damnation, how are they gravell'd in their thoughts when they obſerve God in his holy word exhibiting himſelf as ſo kind and benign a Lover of Mankind, ſo unlikely to hate originally any thing he makes, that he does never <hi>willingly grieve nor afflict the Children of men.</hi> On the other hand when ſome are peremptorily rejecting all doctrines of this Nature, how do they ſtick and labour under the inexplicable difficulty of Divine fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein therefore, we ſhould all imitate the Modeſty of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who yet had the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of brighter revelations than ever we can pretend to. He, when he had been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing that difference it had pleas'd God to put betwixt the Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> and all the reſt of mankind, reſults the whole in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> — <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the Wiſdom and of the Knowledge of God; how unſearchable are his judgments and his ways paſt finding out!</hi> Rom. 11.34, 35.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Laſt. Come we to conſider, laſtly, how ſhort and imperfect we are in our knowledge of God, as to his works either of Creation or Providence.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97879:8"/>
1. The works of his Creation. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Elihu</hi> to confirm what he had ſaid in the words of my Text appeals to the Works of his Creation, and inſtances in ſo ſmall a thing as a drop of Water, the breaking of a Cloud, and a clap of Thunder. <hi>Behold God is great and we know him not—For the maketh ſmall the drops of water, they pour down rain according to the Vapour thereof, which the Clouds do drop, and diſtill upon man abundantly; Alſo can any underſtand the ſpreading of the Clouds, or the noiſe of his Tabernacles,</hi> v. 27, 28, 29.</p>
            <p>It is from theſe works of his, that it pleaſes God to humble <hi>Job,</hi> by laying them before him, and thereby giving him a view of his own ignorance, Job 38.16. <hi>Haſt thou enter'd into the Springs of the Sea, or haſt thou walkt in the ſearch of the deep? Have the gates of death been open'd to thee, or haſt thou ſeen the doors of the ſhadow of death? Haſt thou perceiv'd the breadth of the Earth? declare if thou knoweſt it at all. Where is the way where light dwelleth, and as for darkneſs, where is the place of it? Haſt thou enter'd into the treaſures of the ſnow, or haſt thou ſeen the treaſures of the hail? Out of whoſe womb came the Ice, and the hoary froſt, who hath
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97879:9"/>gender'd it? Canſt thou bind the ſweet influences of the Pleiades, or looſe the bands of Orion? Canſt thou bring forth Mazaroth in his ſeaſon, or canſt thou guide Arcturus with his Sons?</hi> &amp;c. We live by conjecture only as to the reaſons and nature of all thoſe things we either ſee or uſe. It is no certain account we can give of the air we breathe in, or the light that gives us the pleaſure of all created glories; not only the Stars of Heaven, but the Spark in the Diamond, and the luſtres we meet with in a clod of Earth, puzzles our deepeſt Philoſophy. Nothing we ſee either in the Air, or Seas, or Earth, or Heaven, but, as they have been mighty ſubjects of enquiry, ſo, they never yet cou'd be ſo explain'd, but that ſome new ſuppoſals of things have been offer'd with as probable reaſons; and the man of ſtrongeſt fancy has uſually made the moſt pleaſing and acceptable gueſſes, and all is but gueſs at laſt.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, how can we expect well to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſecrets of nature at a diſtance, when we know ſo little nearer home. We carry about with us in the nature of our own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſuch numberleſs and inſuperable difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that they are never to be ſolv'd till the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97879:9"/>Soul comes nearer to its firſt original, and the body is refin'd from its corruption and droſs, that the whole man may diſcern him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (if I may ſo expreſs it) in his own tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency. Let our thoughts therefore turn a little inward, and ſee what conjectures we can make about our own frame and nature, and this perhaps, will let us ſee how ſhort our ſight is, as to all the other great works of the Creation. This obſervation the wiſe man makes Eccl. 11.5. <hi>As thou knoweſt not what is the way of the Spirit, nor how the bones do grow in the womb of her that is with Child, even ſo thou knoweſt not the works of God that maketh all.</hi> The Spirit that enlivens and actuates us, lyes hid from us in the whole courſe of its motion, diſcourſe, or thinking. We know we ſubſiſt of ſomething that can diſcourſe and think, can grieve and rejoice, can remember and reflect; but that Soul it ſelf that does all this, by all its reaſoning, can give no account how it came into the body, nor where the ſeat of its own reſidence is, nor by what way or influence it gives the body ſenſe or motion. It never yet has ſeen its own face in any glaſs that cou'd give it any tolerable repreſentation
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97879:10"/>of it ſelf, but muſt wait the time when it ſhall arrive at its own proper Countrey, that world of Spirits, where the body it ſelf ſhall be ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualiz'd, and come ſo much nearer to the nature of that being that informs, and is to dwell for ever in it. But further</p>
            <p n="2">2. As our inſight into the works of Gods creation is ſhort and imperfect, ſo is it no leſs into thoſe of his providence. We are apt to wonder and ſtand amazd at many unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table events in the world, and many times can diſcern no other reaſon but the meer ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary will of God. Several perplexing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſoments about the age and firſt birth of the World: Why of no earlier a date than 7000 years ago? About the fall of man, why permitted to be ſo ſoon baffled by the Devil? About the great myſtery of Redemption, why to be brought about by no leſs a method than the incarnation and death of the Son of God? About the proſperity of ſome Kingdoms, and the overthrow of others; about particular events of providence to our ſelves, our friends, or our enemies; and innumerable inſtances of this kind, that may perplex and confound our thoughts; but we muſt expect to have no
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97879:10"/>tolerable account of them, till we come to that ſtate where all ſtories will be told over again, all amazing revolutions of things ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd fully in their firſt cauſes, and their laſt iſſues; where wiſdom will juſtifie it ſelf in all the intricacies of its operations, and the great Judge of all ſhall be <hi>clear</hi> indeed when he <hi>hath judged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much may ſerve for illuſtrating the argument, <hi>viz.</hi> how infinitely ſhort we are, in our higheſt conceptions of God, as to any juſt and adequate knowledge of him, if we conſider either his nature, or his decrees and counſels, or his works either of creation or providence.</p>
            <p>Come we now to ſome uſeful inferences from the whole.</p>
            <p n="1">I. From all that has been ſaid we learn what an ineſtimable treaſure the H. Scriptures ought to be eſteem'd by us: Wherein it has pleas'd God to make known himſelf ſo far as our natures in this preſent condition of life, are capable of apprehending him. It is very little that we could ever have conjectur'd aright concerning God without ſome revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of himſelf, in what method he himſelf
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97879:11"/>pleas'd. It is indeed but little he has given us leave to know of him in this world, by all that he hath told us in his word: But herein are we bleſt and priviledg'd indeed, that hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this free uſe of the H. Scriptures, if we will learn not to be wiſe beyond what revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion has thought fit to teach us, we may be ſure that all the knowledge of God which we acquire from the H. Scriptures, is moſt unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionably true, becauſe they are the dictates of that H. Spirit, who only knows the nature, and counſels, and operations of God, and is himſelf, the God that <hi>cannot lye</hi> or deceive us. And beſides that, what we learn of God from the H. Scriptures is unqueſtionably true, ſo, we ſhall not be accountable for what we do not know of God, if we make the Scriptures our guide, becauſe therein is contained the whole revelation of the divine Nature, ſo far as he is pleaſed to indulge it to us in this World. If we ſubmit our ſpeculations of God to theſe <hi>lively oracles,</hi> by which, and by which alone, he hath taken care we ſhould know any thing of him, we are ſafe from all the falſe flights of Superſtition on the one hand, Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſm on the other hand, and all the wandring
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97879:11"/>miſguided opinions concerning God on every hand. Here we may ſet our foot, and acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſce in what we certainly meet with here, tho we may not be carried into thoſe heights to which ſome vain opiniaſtres think they could be ſoaring, or tho there may be ſome my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries which leave our reaſon behind them, and call in for the aſſiſtance of Faith as believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they are the certain matter of revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which muſt therefore be true, becauſe revealed to us by the H. Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>There are two things wherein the <hi>Socinians</hi> have ſeemed to lay a barr againſt themſelves as to the ſoundneſs of their Faith.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The looſe conceptions about the Divine inſpiration of the H. Scriptures. 2. Their appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion that they muſt believe nothing, which their own reaſons cannot comprehend. By the former, they let go that firm hold they ought to have of ſome firſt principles, on which they ought to reſt and depend, and lay themſelves open to a gradual Scepticiſm throughout the whole Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomy of Faith. And by the other they diſcard all myſtery in Religion, and would pretend to fathom the utmoſt depths of that, while they are uncapable of ſolving a thouſand difficulties
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97879:12"/>in every thing which they ſee and handle, and converſe immediately with. Hence their he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitating in the great myſtery of our redemption by Chriſt Jeſus, and the ſatisfaction to divine juſtice effected by his death; the deep and unfathomable doctrine of the Trinity in Unity, and Unity in Trinity. They forget the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority that matters of pure revelation ought to have with our Belief, and that where our reaſon cannot reach they muſt not therefore cry out of Contradiction and Impoſſibility, becauſe we cannot tell what is contradictory or what is impoſſible, where we cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the nature of that thing about which we are apt to ſuſpect an impoſſibility; unleſs it appear contradictory to ſomething that is plainly revealed. It is therefore a good Caution of the Apoſtles which he gives, and that in a peculiarly ſmart turn of words, which he has hardly us'd more than this one time through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his whole writings. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Not to think more highly than he ought to think but to think ſoberly.</hi> Rom. 21.3. Let this be the meaſure we take in all matters of pure revelation, firſt to ſatisfy our ſelves, that this or that thing is unqueſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97879:12"/>reveal'd, and then, how inſuperable ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the difficulties may ſeem that attend it, not to perplex our ſelves in nicely unfolding them, but give Reaſon only the ſcope of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing the neceſſity of believing what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd, and after ſubmitting the whole myſtery of it to the obedience of faith. And this will infinitely endear to us the H. Scriptures where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we know is contain'd the whole compaſs of knowledge concerning God, which we ought to aſpire after in this world.</p>
            <p n="2">II. We may hence alſo infer how reaſonable a thing it is for us to love one another in ſome differences of thought and opinion while we are on this ſide heaven. Our knowledge of God is ſcanty and imperfect, and in our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect way of thinking it is hardly poſſible not to think differently, where therefore any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in opinion have no influences to a bad life, nor diſturb the government, nor lead to a neceſſity of throwing off the Authority of the Scriptures, there, our mutual love and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance (whatever elſe is) is a moſt undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed command.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Laſt We may hence infer, how juſtly the wiſe and the good mind may be longing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97879:13"/>after that ſtate where their knowledge of God may be advanc'd to ſuch unſpeakable degrees, ſuitably both to the nature of God, and the capacious nature of our Souls. Alas! What is all this World (in compariſon) but igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and miſtake! Where fancy chiefly proves the guide to reaſon, and in recompence to all its travels in <hi>Worldly</hi> knowledge, gives it little other ſatisfaction than cheat and deluſion! With what ſatisfaction can the wiſe mind linger and trifle here, diſtant from home, and a ſtranger to the intereſts and affairs of its own Country above! Coopt up and confin'd to a place where ſo little light is; converſing hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with any thing, but the ſhapes and images of things, which a trivial fancy or a diſeas'd eye is framing to it ſelf. It is in the other World only that the Soul can bath it ſelf in the pure, and clear ſtreams of rational knowledge. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, that we <hi>ſee but through a glaſs darkly,</hi> and <hi>we know but in part;</hi> i. e. it is but little we ſee at moſt, and but uncertainly at beſt. <hi>But when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part ſhall be done away.</hi> 1 Cor. 13.9, 10, 11, 12. Then as to the nature, and decrees, and works of God, <hi>We ſhall ſee</hi> all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97879:13"/>
               <hi>face to face, and know even as we are known,</hi> v. 12. That will be the <hi>land of Viſion</hi> indeed; where all things ſhall be ſeen as they are, where all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations ſhall ceaſe, and metaphors prove uſeleſs. Where every riddle ſhall be explain'd to the utmoſt ſatisfaction of greedieſt enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers into the deep things of God. Then, tho the Divine Nature be ſo boundleſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite that it ſurpaſſes the thoughts and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of Angels themſelves, yet will both Angels and Men ſo far comprehend the nature and being of God, that they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver entertain any unworthy or uncomely thoughts of him more: They ſhall never frame to themſelves any mean and wretched images of God, but ſhall <hi>ſee him as he is;</hi> and that ſo ſubſtantially, and ſo much in reality, that the very ſight will, in ſome meaſure, transform them into his image, and make them like him whom they thus view. So <hi>S. John</hi> tells us, <hi>Behold now we are the ſons of God,</hi> (1 Joh. 3.2.) <hi>and it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be; but we know when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> We ſhall not then ſee the <hi>back parts</hi> only, as it once pleas'd God to indulge to <hi>Moſes</hi> in this world,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97879:14"/>but we ſhall be able fully and ſubſtantially to contemplate his nature, ſo as to acquieſce in the knowledge of him, as a moſt ſure and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluble bond of eternal Converſe and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him. <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> Matth. 5.8.</p>
            <p>And as they ſhall ſee him in his <hi>Nature,</hi> ſo they ſhall ſee him in his <hi>Decrees</hi> too. Then all the difficult knots of the divine foreknowledge ſhall be unty'd. We ſhall then ſee how the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of mans will conſiſted with Gods praeſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? that this latter did not influence the former, as to a neceſſity of the mans ſinning and undoing himſelf, but that he himſelf was the author and firſt mover in both. S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> after he had ſo poſitively aſſerted and with ſo much heat argu'd the doctrines of Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, yet was he ſo conſcious of his being in the dark in theſe things, that he made it one comfortable ſpeculation in his thoughts about Heaven and the other ſtate, that he ſhould then come to underſtand the vaſt myſtery of God's decrees, in what method they were diſpos'd, and what influences they had or had not upon mankind.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97879:14"/>
Then (in a word) will all the glories of the Creation unveil themſelves? then will all the intricacies of divine Providence be unravell'd, and the juſt connexion of every link in that great Chain, will be ſeen plainly, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ador'd. Then all our perplext enquiries into the reaſons of ſtrange and unaccountable events will be moſt tranſportingly ſatisfy'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then all the murmuring and oblique reflections we have raſhly caſt upon Providence in this world, ſhall turn into praiſes and adorations, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring and owning that infinite wiſdom that has run through all the turns and windings of humane affairs, and made all ſeeming contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of action and event, conſpire in one great and ſubſervient deſign of Gods glory, and the eternal well-being of thoſe that have truſted in, and depended upon him. As God will then call all the actions of men to a ſevere and particular account, ſo will he condeſcend to give as fair and treatable reaſons of his dealings in this world to the perfect ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all happy beings, and to the ſurprizing Confuſion of Devils, and bad men; when <hi>they</hi> ſhall ſee how much the miſchiefs (wherein God permitted them to be ſo ſucceſsful and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97879:15"/>proſperous for a time) tended not only to their own miſery and undoing, but to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of thoſe very Perſons happineſs whom they ſo much diſdained and hated: which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may be not obſcurely intimated in that paſſage <hi>we ſhall know as we are known.</hi> That is, as God will ſift all our actions, and make his diſtinct enquiries what we have had and done in the world, ſo will he lay before us all his own methods, and ſhow us all the juſt and wiſe reaſons of his providence in this world. Then <hi>David</hi> whoſe <hi>feet had well-nigh ſlipt when he ſaw the proſperity of the wicked;</hi> and <hi>Jeremy</hi> who would have been pleading the caſe with God here, <hi>wherefore the way of the wicked ſhould proſper, and all they be happy that had dealt very treacherouſly:</hi> Nay I may add, then, all thoſe bleeding Souls, that have been ſo long crying under the Altar, <hi>How long Lord, Holy and true, doſt thou not judge and avenge our blood upon them that dwell upon the Earth!</hi> they ſhall all joyn in one conſort, and make infinite harmony before the wiſe and faithful God, in that Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> and of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> which comprehends the whole Church of God under both diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, <hi>Great and marvelous are thy works, Lord
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97879:15"/>God Almighty; juſt and true are thy ways, O thou King of Saints,</hi> Rev. 15.3. What wiſe and good mind, ſhould not long for this mighty advance into the knowledge of God, where the knowledge of him will be ſo tranſporting and ſatisfactory, and will advance mankind to ſuch degrees of likeneſs and conformity with God. To this glorious ſtate of knowledge and enjoyment of himſelf, the Bleſſed God bring us all through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, to whom with himſelf and the eternal Spirit of grace be rendered, as is moſt due, all honour, and glory and praiſe, both now and for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:97879:16"/>
            <head>BOOKS lately Printed, for <hi>Tho. Bennet,</hi> at the <hi>Half-Moon,</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church yard.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>AThena O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onienſes.</hi> An Exact Hiſtory of all the Writers and Biſhops who have had their Education in the moſt ancient and famous Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> from the Fifteenth Year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, <hi>Dom.</hi> 1500, to the End of the Year. 1690. Repreſenting the Birth, Fortune, Preferment, and death of all thoſe Authors and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, the great Accidents of their Lives, and the Fate and Character of their Writings. To which are added the <hi>Faſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or Annals of the ſaid Univerſity, for the ſame time. The firſt Volume extending to the 10th Year of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. <hi>Dom.</hi> 1640.</p>
            <p>The Second Volume extending to 1691, is in the Preſs, and will be publiſhed with all poſſible Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Plagiary Expoſed:</hi> Or an Old Anſwer to a New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Revived Calumny againſt the Memory of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. Being a Reply to a Book intitled King <hi>Charle</hi>'s Caſe, Formerly Written by <hi>John Cook</hi> of <hi>Grays</hi> Inn, Barriſter; and ſince Copied out under the Title of Collonel <hi>Ludlow</hi>'s Letter. Written by Mr. <hi>Butler,</hi> the Author of <hi>Hudibras.</hi> And never before Printed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Critical Hiſtory of the New-Teſtament,</hi> In two Parts, by Father <hi>Simon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Reaſons of Mr.</hi> Bay's <hi>Changing his Religion,</hi> In Three Parts. The Second Edition.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97879:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
